Guide to the Henry Samuel Hacker Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Henry Samuel Hacker collection
1927-2001
1927-1947
MS 1612
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
(4 boxes, 2 folios)
The collection comprises printed material, including books, posters, postcards, and related ephemera, that pertain to the country of Germany, its people, history, and culture. The bulk of the material relates to the Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei (Nazi Party). The majority of items cover the years 1927 to 1947.
Hacker, Henry Samuel, 1942-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry S. Hacker, 1991, 1992, and 2001.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Samuel Hacker was born on December 26, 1942, in New York City. He graduated from Yale College in 1945 with a B.A., majoring in history. He has worked as an attorney and as executive vice-president of Alexander Julian, Inc. He is married to Andrea M. Prager with whom he has had three children. He is a collector of memorabilia from Nazi-Germany and the 1972 Olympic Games held in Munich.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises printed materials, including books, posters, postcards, and related ephemera, that pertain to the country of Germany, its people, history, and culture. The bulk of the material relates to the Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei (Nazi Party). The majority of items cover the years 1927 to 1947.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by accession.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection must be used under the supervision of a Manuscripts and Archives Public Services staff member.
National socialism; Nazi propaganda; Germany -- Politics and government -- 1933-1945; Nuremberg (Germany); Posters; Hacker, Henry Samuel, 1942-; Hitler, Adolf, 1889-1945; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei. Reichsparteitag; Nationalsozialistisches Fliegerkorps; Olympic Games (11th) ( 1936 Berlin, Germany); Olympic Games (20th) ( 1972 Munich, Germany)
- Inventory, 1936, 1940-1941
  - Tages Programm, XI Olympische Spiele, Berlin, 1936 August 3 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    An official program from the 1936 Olympic Games (11th Olympiad) held in Berlin, Germany. The program contains lists of the International Olympic Committee members and officials and provides a list of the events held on August 3rd.
  - Posters of the Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei (Nazi Party)
    - Das ging gründlich daneben!!, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Altes britisches "Motto" - neu frisiert, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Offene Worte aus London, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Führer befiehl -wir folgen!, 1941 (Box 2)
    - "..und kein Kompromiss!", 1941 (Box 2)
    - Das muss festgehalten werden!, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Dokumente des Verrates, 1941 (Box 2)
- Additional Material, 1972; Accession 1993-M-037
  - Olympische Spiele München 1972 (Box 1)
    A series of five posters commemorating the Olympic Games (20th Olympiad) in Munich.
- Additional Material, 1927-1947, 2001; Accession 2002-M-044
  This accession comprises two cigarette card albums and a collection of Nazi-era ephemera that includes a booklet of sketches, a calendar, cut-outs, postage stamps, postcards, posters, rally passes, a sticker, and telegrams. The bulk of the material consists of postcards and telegrams.
  - Books
    - Auf Deutscher Scholle, von Hans von der Nordmark, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Translated as "Out of German Soil," this cigarette card book is divided into chronological sections relating primarily to various aspects of German agriculture. Each section has descriptive text, interspersed with empty boxes for pasting in picture labels, corresponding to captions throughout. The picture labels were available by exchanging them for tokens from cigarette packs. Written in German script.
    - Bilder Deutscher Geschichte, werk 12, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      A cigarette card book depicting events in German history from the Middle Ages to 1914. Written in German script.
  - Nazi-Era Ephemera
    Arrangement
    Items are arranged to mirror the order in the "Guide to Nazi-Era Ephemera" in box 1, folder 3; namely, alphabetically by the category of the items. Within each category, items are listed numerically by identification numbers (supplied by the collector) which are sequential within a category only. Identification numbers appear in parentheses after the item.
    - Guide to "Nazi-era Ephemera", 2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The detailed guide, compiled by collector Samuel S. Hacker, depicts a color image of each item; an identification number; the type or category of the item; date; title; a description of the subject matter in German and English; and the dimensions of the item. Many descriptions of individual items in the guide have been used in the finding aid.
    - Booklet (2081-1 to 2081-23)
      - Back From Hell, Collected Sketches, by Berl Friedler, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        A collection of bound sketches depicting images of Nazi aggression, the Holocaust, and atrocities at concentration camps. Printed with the assistance of the Central Committee of Liberated Jews in the British Zone of Germany and the American Joint Distribution Committee for the British Zone, 1947.
    - Calendar (2080) with images of German political and military figures., 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Cut-outs (2041-2049), Undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      A set of nine sheets of paper cut-outs, depicting military figures marching, saluting, and carrying Nazi banners; and members of the Jugend.
    - Postage stamps (2027), Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Judenpost Litzmannstadt-Getto. A set of three stamps of different denominations with the Star of David, the profile of an unidentified figure, and imagery relating to industrial production, including factory smokestacks, a gearwheel, scissors, and a spool of thread.
    - Postcards (2003-2018, 2050, 2056-2057, and 2067)
      Postcards, numbers 2003-2018, 2050, 2056-2057, and 2067, pertain to Nazi rallies. A rally, Reichsparteitag, was the meeting of the Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei (NSDAP) or Nazi Party, from 1923-1938. With the exception of the first and second rallies, (Munich, 1923, and Weimar, 1926, respectively), they were held at the Nazi party rally grounds in Nuremberg, a city located in the center of the German Reich, from 1927-1938.
      - Nürnberg, die Stadt der Reichsparteitage (2003), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts Nuremberg as the city of the party rallies. Watercolor view of the city, showing a parade through the streets, spectators, and buildings decorated with Nazi flags, wreaths, and banners.
      - Nürnberg, die Stadt der Reichsparteitage. Adolf' Hitler Platz (2004), Circa 1927 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Postcard of Nuremberg's Adolf Hitler Square, showing large outdoor umbrellas in the square and some of the surrounding architecture. Lower half of the postcard is an advertisement for the Lumophon radios, made in Nuremberg, and shows the factory building.
      - Zur Erinnerung an den Reichsparteitag 1934. Der NSDAP zu Nürnberg (2005) (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Souvenir postcard of the 1934 Nuremberg rally with image of Nuremberg castle.
      - Reichsparteitag-Gelände in Nürnberg. Gesamtplan (2006), Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts a site map of the Nuremberg rally campus.
      - Reichs - Parteitag - Nürnberg (2007), Circa 1935 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Stamps depict a similar composition to the postcard; eagle with swastika wreath hovering above Nuremberg castle.
      - Reichsparteitag - Nürnberg (2008), Circa 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts symbols of heraldry.
      - Zur Erinnerung an den Reichsparteitag der NSDAP (2009), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Photograph of Nuremberg Castle.
      - Postcard with photograph of Hitler in Nuremberg in 1923 (2010), 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        On verso: Nürnberg 1923. Herausgegeben von der N. S. Volkswohlfahrt.
      - Sammelt Euch im NS Reichskriegerbund (2011), Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Invitation to attend a meeting of the NS (Nationalsozialistischer) Reich's fighter federation.
      - Reichsparteitag - Nürnberg (2012), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts uniformed soldier bearing shovel and backpack at rally.
      - Reichsparteitag Nürnberg (2013), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts young girl in uniform. Postage stamp is from Czechoslovakia.
      - 1927 Reichsparteitag Nürnberg 1937 (2014) (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Commemorates ten years of rallies.
      - Reichsparteitag Nürnberg (2015), Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts soldier marching in formation; Nuremberg Castle in background.
      - Grossdeutscher Reichsparteitag (2016), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Postcard from the first great German rally depicting a red map of Germany, superimposed over a stylized eagle.
      - Reichsparteitag Nürnberg 1937 (2017) (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts the rally stadium with Nazi flags.
      - Reichsparteitag Nürnberg (2018), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Depicts a young girl in uniform.
      - Reichs-Parteitag 1938 Nürnberg (2050) (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Reichsparteitag-Nürnberg (2056), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Depicts German in uniform with Nazi flag. Cancellation stamp reads Parteitag Grossdeutschlands.
      - Ein Volk Ein Reich Ein Führer Reichsparteitag Nürnberg (2057), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Depicts a collage of coats of arms surrounding image of a golden swastika.
      - Reichsparteitag Nürnberg N.S.D.A.P. (2067), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Depicts Nazi postage stamps bearing Hitler's likeness.
      - Baufahrt der Alten Kämpfer der Bayerischen Ostmark (2019), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Describes a tour to sites pertaining to fighters of Bavarian East Germany, highlighting the Dietrich Eckart Memorial and the Walhalla, a building resembling the Parthenon in Athens.
      - Nationalsozialistisches Fliegerkorps (NSFK)
        Postcards, numbers 2020-2023, and 2025, pertain to the Nationalsozialistisches Fliegerkorps (National Socialist Flyers Corps) established by Hitler, April 17, 1937, to take over military pilot training from the Deutscher Luftsport-Verband (German Air Sports Association).
        - NSFK (2020), 1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
          On verso: Das NS-Fliegerkorps ruft die Jugend zum Dienst in der Luftfahrt- (Calling the youth to service in aviation).
        - Lernt Fliegen! (2021), Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
          Depicts close-up of a pilot in cockpit in flight.
        - On verso: Nationalsozialistisches Fliegerkorps (2022), Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
          Depicts a yellow propeller plane in midair with "D-E HAK" on its wings.
        - Fliegen lernen! (2023), Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
          Depicts a young pilot in a biplane.
        - On verso: Die jüngste Nachwuchs der Luftwaffe wird durch das NS-Fliegerkorps im Modellflug ausgebildet (2025), Undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
          Depicts a young boy in uniform setting off a model airplane in flight.
      - On verso: Deutsche Luftsport=Verband. Werde Mitglied! (2024), Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Postcard for the German Air Sports Association.
      - Enzian Division 1940-1944. Serbien. Ukraine. Kaukasus (2026) (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Postcard for the Enzian Division commemorating its four year anniversary. Grouped with a pamphlet, Ein Ruhmesblatt in der Geschichte der Division, by Uffz. J. M. Rubner.
      - Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei. Sturmabteilung (SA) (2028-2033), 1938-circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Covers depict SA (storm troopers) uniformed soldiers in various work activities; no text.
      - Waffen-SS
        Postcards 2034-2035 pertain to a para-military body created by NSDAP, making up the armed wing of the Schutzstaffel ("Protective Squadron") or SS, an organ of the Nazi Party.
        - Melde Dich freiwillig zu den Gebirgstruppen der Waffen-SS (2034), Circa 1942 (Box 1, Folder 15)
          Postcard for the mountain troops of the SS.
        - Deutsche Jugend meldet sich freiwillig zur Waffen-SS (2035), Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
          Postcard for the Hitler youth to join the SS.
      - Und Ihr habt dock gesiegt! (2036), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Official remembrance postcard from 1938 November 9 depicting three Germans in different uniforms, bearing the Nazi flag.
      - Der Stahlhelm marschiert! (2037), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Postcard reproduction of an original drawing by Heinz Wever-Berlin depicting the Stahlhelm marching. Stahlhelm is German for steel helmet, and refered often to frontline soldiers.
      - On verso: Flak auf Wacht (2038), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Depicts a mother and her children harvesting wheat in foreground, with a flaksoldaten (aircraft spotter) in background.
      - Siedlung NSG "Kraft durch Freude" (2039), Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Depicts a large housing development in a coal field. NSG refers to Neue Shütz-Gesellschaft.
      - On verso: Ins dritte Reich (2051), 1927 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        Reproduction of oil painting depicting a visionary interpretation of the Third Reich.
      - Arbeit adelt (2052), 1933 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        Depicts three workers looking at a monument with Hitler's image and the saying, Arbeit adelt (work is ennobling).
      - 14. Parteigrundungstag 24. u. 25 Febr 1934 (2053) (Box 1, Folder 22)
        Depicts stylized hand with two fingers raised, as in salute to an eagle, and a swastika wreath.
      - Reichsnährstand. Blut und Boden. Reichsbauerntag Goslar 1938 (2054) (Box 1, Folder 23)
        Blood and soil.
      - Pünktlich wie die Eisenbahn! (2055), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Depicts railroad worker signalling the trains in front of the face of a large stop watch.
      - On verso: Innenansicht der Ehrenhalle der Nationalsozialisten Buchholz, Kreis Harburg/W. (2058), Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
        Depicts interior view of the Nazi Hall of Honor.
      - W Hitler. W Mussolini. Anno XVI. Pace Civiltà Lavoro (2059), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        Depicts medallion portraits of Hitler and Mussolini; Nazi and Fascist (?) flag.
      - 1238/1938. Lößnitz im Erzegebirge. 700 Jahrfeier u. Heimatfest 23.-31. Juli 1938 (2060) (Box 1, Folder 27)
        Celebrates the 700 year anniversary of town of Lößnitz (also spelled Lössnitz).
      - On verso: Tag der Deutschen Polizei 1941 (2061) (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Celebrates the day of the German police.
      - Tag der Deutschen Kunst München 1937 16. - 18. Juli (2062) (Box 1, Folder 29)
        Celebrates the day of German art.
      - Das Tausendjährige Gera 700 Jahre Stadt 1237 1937 (2063) (Box 1, Folder 30)
        Celebrates the 700 year anniversary of the city of Gera.
      - Grosser Preis von Europa für Motorräder auf dem Sachsenring bei Hohenstein-Ernstthal am 7. August 1938 (2064) (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Depicts a motorcycle race and spectators, with Nazi, Italian (Fascist?), and English flags.
      - Alpenland Deutsch u. Frei. Untergruppe Alpenland West (2065), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        Depicts Nazi flag with swastika wreath above alpine landscape.
      - Deutsches Erntedankfest (2066), 1936 (Box 1, Folder 33)
        Celebrates the German harvest.
      - 28 Novembre 1937. 28 Nendor 1937. 25 Vjet Shqipni. 25 Années d'Albanie (2068), 2068 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        Twenty-five years of Albania.
    - Poster (2076)
      - Die NSDAP Sichert die Volks-Gemeinschaft. Volksgenossen braucht ihr Rat und Hilfe so wendet euch an die Ortsgruppe, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 35)
        Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei (NSDAP) celebrates the German family.
    - Rally passes (2001-2002), Reichsparteitag Parteikongress, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Admission tickets to the 1937 and 1938 Nuremberg rallies.
    - Sticker (2040), Nordseebad Norderney ist Judenfrei, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      The North Sea beach is free from Jews. Depicts female bather.
    - Telegrams (2069-2075, 2077-2079)
      The telegrams, also called telegram cards, resemble oversize greeting cards, with an image or design on the cover, space for a greeting inside, and a back cover. Deutsche Reichspost may appear on the front or back covers. Telegrams from the 1930s usually have the image of an eagle on a swastika wreath.
      - Deutsche Reichspost (2069), Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
        Depicts an engraving of a winding river and trees.
      - Nürnberg die Stadt der Reichsparteitage. Deutsche Reichspost (2070), 1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Depicts city of Nuremberg with swastika at bottom center, flanked by two coats of arms.
      - Watercolor of Hitler standing in a motor vehicle, giving Nazi salute; rendering of Nuremberg Castle in distance (2071), Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - On back cover: Garnisonkirche zu Potsdam (2072), 1933 March 21 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Cover depicts an eagle soaring above a row of Nazi flags. Back cover shows view of Potsdam's Garnisonkirche (church).
      - Deutsche Reichspost (2073), 1933 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Cover shows silhouette image of a trumpeting figure on horseback, packet in hand, possibly a telegram courier.
      - Deutscher Reichstelegraph (2074), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Depicts woodcut of an engagement/wedding procession. Message inside.
      - Deutsche Reichspost Telegramm (2075), 1929 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Depicts two stylized doves carrying ribbons. Message inside.
      - Deutsche Reichspost (2077), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Depicts a rococo-style wreath of flowers, cupids, and doves. Message inside.
      - Deutsche Reichspost (in German script) (2078), 1936 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Depicts babies and children playing with toys. Message inside.
      - Deutsche Reichspost (2079), 1941 (Box 2, Folder 12)
        Depicts a mountain landscape. Includes envelope with eagle on a swastika wreath, printed in red.
    - Print sheet of six color images promoting the Reichsparteitag Nürnberg, Undated (Box 3)
      Some images used for postcards pictured in the guide to Nazi-era ephemera. Verso depicts unidentified landscape painting.